# Joe Shields

Mechanical engineer with 8 years of design and manufacturing experience Located in Portland, Oregon

Looking for either fully remote work or hybrid work in Cascadia (<40% of working hours in-office) *Not* open to work in the war, fossil-fuels, or animal agriculture industries

Please email before calling: <u>joedang100@gmail.com</u>, 971-226-9393 Read more at Joedang.github.io.

# **Professional Experience**

## Optomechanical Design Engineer, Earth and Space Institute and AirPhoton

Oct. 2021 – July 2023

- Rescued a 20-million-dollar project by applying physical scaling laws
- Halved the size of three separate systems through clever architecture changes
- Performed space-claim, keep-out-zone, and tolerance analyses
- Designed cameras and optical calibration systems
- Managed system requirements, interfaces, and performance
- Designed optics by manually tracing rays in Autodesk Inventor
- Coordinated with contractors, customers, scientists, and engineers to write system specifications
- Designed orbital, airborne, and ground-based instruments
- Solved multi-disciplinary design constraints (mechanical, optical, pneumatic, thermal, etc.)

### Mechanical Lead, Portland State Aerospace Society (PSAS)

Sep. 2019 - Oct. 2021

- Mentored student projects and assembled project teams
- Maintained equipment and lab space
- Performed FMEA and root-cause analysis
- · Managed interdisciplinary projects among students and professionals

# Lab Manager, <u>PSU Electronics Prototyping Lab</u>

Sep. 2019 – Oct. 2021

- Maintained equipment and lab space
- Trained students on prototyping equipment
- Ran the lab's parts store

## Engineer, SpaceX

Mar. 2019 – Sep. 2019

- Supported a wide variety of mechanisms on the human-rated Dragon 2 docking systems
- Wrote detailed and intuitive assembly instructions to meet strict quality standards
- Owned aggressive build schedules and held others accountable to them
- Solved issues including design errors, part damage, missing parts, and documentation errors

Joe Shields' Resume updated: 2024-08-02 page: 1/3

### R&D Engineer, Pacific Diabetes Technologies

Sep. 2018 – Feb. 2019

- Prototyped wearable micro-fluidic devices and electronic enclosures
- Created designs, models, and drawings for patent applications
- Designed miniaturized assemblies for 3D printing and injection molding

# Mechanical Lead, Portland State Aerospace Society (PSAS)

Dec. 2015 - Mar. 2019

- <u>Created an open-hardware carbon fiber rocket airframe</u> for the <u>Portland State Aerospace Society</u>
- Published and presented <u>a conference paper on the project for AIAA SPACE 2016</u>
- Documented design and manufacturing processes to foster institutional knowledge
- Designed parts using hand calculations, prototypes, computer models, CFD, and CAD

### Design Engineer, OreSat

Jan. 2017 – Mar. 2019

- Coordinated the design of all mechanical subsystems in <u>Oregon's first satellite</u>
- Maintained the top-level SolidWorks assembly of the satellite
- Incorporated constraints from NASA, NanoRacks, and OreSat electrical subsystems
- Worked across engineering disciplines to resolve highly coupled designs
- Led analysis and design reviews

#### Lab Manager, Electronics Prototyping Lab

Jan. 2018 – Mar. 2019

Same duties listed above

# **Physical Tools**

3D printers (FDM, SLA, SLS, MJP), laser cutters, mills, lathes, hand tools PCB routers, soldering (hand, re-flow), oscilloscopes, various microscopes Composites manufacturing (wet, dry, high/low-temperature), metal working

## **Software Tools**

Inventor, SolidWorks, NX, Teamcenter, Onshape, OpenSCAD, AutoCAD R, MATLAB, C++, Python, Bash, Vim, Git, Jekyll, HTML, CSS, JavaScript LaTeX, Microsoft Office, Libre Office, Google Docs, et cetera Linux, Windows, Abaqus, GIMP, Inkscape

#### **Education**

# Portland State University, Sep. 2013 - Jun. 2016

- B.S. **Mechanical Engineering**, Maseeh College of Engineering and Computer Science
  - Focus: heat and mass transfer
- B.S. **Physics**, College of Liberal Arts and Sciences
  - Focus: classical mechanics and electromagnetism

## Portland Community College, Sep. 2008 - Jun. 2010, Sep. 2011 - Sep. 2013

Focus: general education, mathematics, music

Joe Shields' Resume updated: 2024-08-02 page: 2/3

# **Small Projects**

In addition to the projects below, you can check out the rest of my portfolio at github.com/Joedang.

- iTopie printer
  - Modified and built a RepRap 3D printer from parts including a custom laser-cut frame
- Restricted 3-body simulation
  - An R script for investigating the motion of satellites within planet-moon systems
- Ballistic trajectory simulation
  - Realistic scenarios of short-range ballistic motion of various projectiles on different planets, accounting for buoyancy, drag, centrifugal, and Coriolis effects written in R
- N-body simulation
  - Various scenarios involving an arbitrary number of charged massive particles written in MATLAB
- OpenFOAM analysis
  - A model of supersonic flow around a rocket nosecone, used to inform the part's design
- PSAS Asset Tracking System
  - Created a specification and front-end in R Shiny for a website to track part maintenance and ownership
- Wearable device enclosure
  - Created a 3D printed enclosure for a wearable sensor prototype for <u>APDM</u> using SolidWorks

#### Miscellaneous

References can be provided upon request.

I'm most interested in design engineering. I work very well with scientists and other engineering disciplines (especially electrical engineers). I perform best with minimal oversight. In my ideal workflow, I spend one to two consecutive days coordinating with team members, and three to four consecutive days hyperfocusing on the tasks identified by that coordination.

Joe Shields' Resume updated: 2024-08-02 page: 3/3